<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The souldiers demand· Shewing their present misery; and prescribing a perfect remedy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E555_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3057</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872264</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872264</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165117</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E555[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The souldiers demand· Shewing their present misery; and prescribing a perfect remedy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Bristoll :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare of intended parity. 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  History, (17th century) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165117:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SOULDIERS DEMAND.</p>
            <p>Shewing Their PRESENT MISERY; And preſcribing A PERFECT REMEDY.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Bristoll</hi> in the Yeare of inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Parity. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:165117:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165117:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>SOULDIERS Demand.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Fellow Souldiers:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT has pleaſed the Lord to open our eyes, and to let us ſee the wretched conditions we are brought under; and our crying ſinnes, which cry aloud in the eares of God. Oh! the Ocean of bloud that we are guilty of. Oh! the intollerable oppreſſion that we have laid upon our Brethren of <hi>England.</hi> Oh! how theſe deadly ſinnes of ours doe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our conſciences? Oh! how are we able to anſwer theſe peſtilent acts of ours, at the dreadfull bar of Gods di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine juſtice? Nay this is the moſt ſharpeſt conflict to them, that we never underſtood a true Cauſe, or juſt reaſon for the ſhedding of ſo much innocent bloud in our own Nation, nor why we have done ſuch horrid oppreſſion to our owne Countrey-men.</p>
            <p>Has not the diſſembling and hypocriticall Parliament gull'd and deceiv'd us by their faire pretences of reforming the Proteſtant Religion, of rectifying the State, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of the ancient Liberties of the People of <hi>England?</hi> Have ye obſerv'd any thing leſſe, or any thing more contrary, ſit hence the Parliament hath been for theſe eight years paſt? We poore ſimple men did verily beleeve that theſe had been the true Cauſes and Reaſons (all this while) for which we have fought thus eagerly one againſt another.</p>
            <p>And ever ſince our Army did firſt enter into the great City of <hi>London,</hi> what Declarations and ſpecious promiſes have been ſet forth to the ſame effect? And doe ye not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, how they walke ſtill in the ſame wayes, yea far worſe every day than other? will you be any longer led by the noſes by theſe deluſions and mockeries, and ſuffer your bodies and ſoules to be utterly ruined? Oh, our worthy Companions,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165117:3"/>and Fellow-Souldiers, be not any longer miſled by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling ſhowes of our Superiours (as we muſt call them) and the wicked Inſtruments, their pretended Parliament, leſt you be tortured in your Conſciences as we are, and make your ſelves the baſeſt ſlaves in the whole world, and eternall ſlaves in Hell hereafter.</p>
            <p>Yet brave Souldiers let us give every body their due; has not brave <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rfax,</hi> and gallant <hi>Crumwell,</hi> and we their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, made the Engliſh and Scottiſh earth to tremble, whereſoever we have ſet our feet? and have not our hands convinced all our foes and oppoſers? and brought gallant <hi>Fairfax</hi> and <hi>Crumwell</hi> to this high pitch of honour, that they have da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to lay their Soveraignes head under their feet, and many of his Nobles in the duſt? and there is not a Lord left, nor any of the gallanteſt men in the whole Kingdome, that dares to budge againſt them: For if they doe require any thing of them, they will rather licke up the duſt under their feet, than dare any manner of way to oppoſe them. Nay further, have not they and we brought the Royall City, the great Metropolis of this Kingdome, to that ſubjection and baſeneſſe, that we dare ſweare on hundred of us (though there be a CM. and a CM. fighting men in it) would drive them out of their Towne, and make them to lye downe at our ſeet like Spannels, and ſuffer themſelves to be baſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoed, and give us whatſoever we would deſire of them, they doe ſo dread a ſouldiers face, and tremble at the very ſight of one? And as for the Countrey poore ſlaves, we have ſo tained, awed, and domineered over them, that we can make them like ſetting-doggs, to come when we call, to doe what we command, and to lye downe when we bid them: And yet theſe baſe peaſants (for we can terme them no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) though they are ſuch milkſops, let any of them be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into our ſociety, and a little impudence put into them, and after they are hardened therein, they will preſently turne Lyons; ſuch gallant ſpirits doth the art of Armes many times put into baſe and ignoble clownes. Oh, out upon theſe vaine Fooleries; what would we give to have our troubled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165117:3"/>ſetled in peace? Oh, this bloud and oppreſſion does more exaſperate us than we are able to expreſſe: If the Lord be not pleaſed to ſhew us mercy, what will become of us, the moſt miſerable of all men?</p>
            <p>And will you not have diſcovered unto you the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of our baſe Generall, and his ſubordinate Officers towards us, and their ſmall eſteeme of us, though we be the only means of their high advancement? Doe they not now raigne and rule above Kings? Is it not by our valour? Is not their owne will a Law, to which every body muſt be ſubject? Or elſe are not we their ſtrength and power, to force and compell all oppoſers to their luſts and pleaſures? Who dares to affront them, that we doe not preſently ſubdue, and make obedient? Have not they likewiſe (by the terror of us) ſet up a Councell of State (forſooth) as they call it, and a Parliament of Knaves, according to their owne humour, to act, force, and order whatſoever our Superiours will have them to doe, that under the name of a Parliament, all their villanies, oppreſſing and cheating of the poore people, muſt be overſhadowed, and varniſhed, as Taxes, Exciſe, and other oppreſſive Acts, firſt ordered, and made by our Superiours, but muſt beare the ſtamp and face of a Parliament: And is it not the terror of us, that makes this baſe Parliament their Bawd and Pander?</p>
            <p>And will you give leave to ſet forth unto you our baſe and vile uſage from theſe Caterpillers, and ungratefull villaines, that very well know how they dare not ſhew their heads in any honeſt place but for us; it is our valour that ſupports them, and if we decline from them, they will fall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume like ſmoke: And yet if we run not like ſlaves to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill their luſts, are we not ſcorned and abuſed, and kicked like dogs by them, as if we were the very ſcumme of the world in their eſteeme? Are we not unpaid our wages and hire by them, by which we ſhould live, and for want of it, are we not forced to get our bread by force and rapine (elſe we muſt ſtarve) from our poore Countrey-men? Have we any clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but at their pleaſure? ſo that for want many of us ſundry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165117:4"/>times are conſtrained to goe to a hedge, or breake into a houſe, or elſe to the High-way; and if any of us be but taken in this miſdemeanor, on what an high offence is it? up we muſt to the gallowes, and be condemned, or cenſured by our Commanders, who are the only reaſon, by their unhoneſt and unjuſt retaining of our wages in their owne fingers, for want whereof we are many of us forced to doe that we ought not to doe. Doe they not upon any occaſion quarrell againſt us? if we be but abſent, or doe not inſtantly what they will have us, are we not cudgelled, horſed, our Armes broken over our heads to our diſgrace? Are we not threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon every ſlight occaſion to be caſhiered, our Arreares to be ſtopped? Have not many of us been hanged and ſhot at their pleaſure? Muſt we not goe and run when they will have us, and whither they will ſend us? Muſt we not lye at their doores day and night like doggs to watch and guard them; elſe, are we not accounted mutinous, and Rebels, and that is a mighty thing with them, and a great care they have to ſuppreſſe it? Do they not make us worſe than the very Janizaries to the Great Turke? For are not they the greateſt enemies to their owne Parents, to their owne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to their owne Countrey? ſo are not we their ſlaves to perſecute our owne Countrey, by killing and fighting with our own brethren, againſt our naturall Parents, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up falſe Religions; by quartering upon them, in eating them up, and famiſhing of many Families theſe hard times, by our waſtfull charge and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yot: when alas, they like miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants, with-hold our pay from us, and force us thus cruelly to devoure them and their children? Are not we their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to fetch in their oppreſſive Taxes from the poore Countrey men? If any poore man has it not to pay, yet we violently take it from him, with much advantage over be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides to our ſelves. Oh the bitter curſes the poore people lay to our charge, anti our Superiours that ſet us a-worke: We are afraid they reach up into the eares of God againſt us; and for theſe unjuſt extortions upon his Children, we ſhall one day receive a ſharp cenſure. Are we not toſſed too
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165117:4"/>and fro over the earth at their pleaſure, or elſe we are Rebels againſt their Greatneſſes, and ſo lyable to what puniſhment they will pleaſe to inflict upon us? Sometimes we muſt march to <hi>London,</hi> by and by downe to <hi>Barwicke</hi> to the Weſt, to the North, to <hi>Scotland,</hi> to <hi>Ireland,</hi> even whither they will; and if they doe but heare of any of the poore people but murmur againſt their oppreſſion and cruelty, do they not preſently ſend us to ſee the matter, and to quaile them? per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, if they be reſolute we muſt kill them, or be killed by them. Do we not expoſe our ſelves to all danger and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, to uphold theſe domineering Raſcals in their pomp and luxury? Doe they not moſt inſolently invaſſall us? Doe they not vilifie us? How baſe and meane are we (in their conceit) to themſelves? Doe they not keep our pay and hire from us, and thruſt us upon the poore people to ſhift for our ſelves? Doe not they themſelves pamper and feaſt their bodies whereſoever they come with the beſt and choiſeſt refreſhments, at other mens Tables? incouch themſelves in the ſumptuous lodgings and furniture? Doe they not live in all delicateneſſe? Doe they not oppreſſe, and violently take away every bodies Right, Inheritance, Poſſeſſion goods, money, treaſure, where and from whom they pleaſe, under the colour of Taxes, Aſſize, and oppoſition againſt the State (as they call it?) Was there ever ſuch a pack of Knaves in the world, and ſuch villany acted as is by them, and all under ſuch faire pretences? It is for the good of State, and the maintaining of the Army, yet the Army muſt be paid as they in their diſcretion ſhall hold fit: For their policy is to pay us ſhort, that ſo we muſt depend upon their courteſie, and crouch and bow downe to them to pray for our owne right, and out of our neceſſity to impoveriſh the State, that we may make them as poore and baſe as they doe ſtrive to make us to themſelves; and we being all poore, and they having gotten all into their owne poſſeſſion, we muſt repaire to them as the young Crowes flye to the old ones for food, or elſe we muſt ſtarve. This is their drift and intent to bring us all to, that they may inſult, and rule us at their pleaſure; and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165117:5"/>when they have it thus, then we muſt come at their becke, and goe when they ſend, or elſe caſhiered, our Arreares con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated, and then what ſhall we doe when we are turned out of their ſervice? Is there any ſuch ſlavery as ours? You Fellow-ſouldiers doe very well know theſe baſe affronts continually, and alwayes, have been put upon us, and you very well may perceive how we have been requited for all our gallant ſervice done for theſe our ingratefull Maſters. One thing more of their baſeneſſe towards us, let me put you in mind of before I have done with them: Can they put a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſhonour upon a Souldier, than to make him a hangman, or an Executioner of his Fellow-Souldier, as they have done many times, and nor very long ſince, to the perpetuall infamy of men of our noble Profeſſion, that we ſhould be hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or executioners of one another, or Gaoller. That man whoſoever has been an actor in any of theſe courſes, let us abhorre and deteſt him, and count him not worthy to be aſſociated in our honourable Society, but caſhiere him out of the Army for a baſe infamous perſon, that would be the executioner of a noble Souldier: Let him be ſhunned as a man of bloud, and hatefull to all men of our Profeſſion, and be a vagabond all his dayes. We need call but your owne experience, to bring theſe wrongs and indignities caſt upon us into your memories, by thoſe that ought moſt to have honoured us; we have undergone the ſervitude of theſe hard Maſters for theſe many yeares, yet hitherto we find no amends, but rather worſe and more inſolency and tyranny every day than other. But if you deſire to be free from this baſe ſervitude (as gallant ſouldiers) we lye under, and cleare your Countrey from theſe oppreſſive villaines, who by their craft and treachery have mounted themſelves into the Seats of Regality, by our only fortitude and prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe, and gaine the love of your native Nation, be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ruled by us, and we will preſent you a way how to vindicate our ſelves from theſe our inthrallers; ſo you will be conſtant and firme one to another, and reſolved in heart and unity of affections one with another, we ſhall not only
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165117:5"/>ſet our ſelves free from our cruell Taskmaſters, but alſo enrich our ſelves out of them, and make them our ſlaves, and the moſt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt abjects upon the earth, howſoever they ſlant it now. Yet we have not done with our Superiours (they doe ſo hang in our teeth) yet not out of any malice to their perſons, but againſt their ignoble and diſcourteous dealing againſt their owne Souldiers, who have done ſo gallantly under their command, doe we further ſet them forth in their lively colours, before we come to our remedy. You may ſee our ſlaviſh condition, that they cunningly and Maſterfully endeavour to keep us under, and to effect their deſignes by us their vaſſals, if we will be any longer ruled by them: And likewiſe you may ſee the advancement we are like to riſe to (by what we have here truly ſet forth) the higheſt is to a paire of gallowes, if they can help us up the ladder, as we ſee their bleſſed good meaning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, if they take us napping under their power. You had a Preſident, and a late and ſad object of this kind lately preſented before you on a Gentleman Souldier of our Army, and many of his Comrades ſent to Newgate: but he poore Gentleman loſt his life for a ſmall matter too, as we have heard, for not ebeying ſome of his Superiours Command. And though many of us under their Commands (for want of underſtanding) have been ſo fooliſh to venture our lives and limbes for their advancement and greatneſſe; yea have not many of our Army loſt their lives and limbs to bring them to this glory, wherein they doe ſo provdly inſult now over us, and their Countrey? but what reward have their wives and children had from them, that have loſt their lives for them? ſome of them a poore penſion of 2 s 6 d <hi>per</hi> weeke, and that not paid them neither. What crying hath been at the Parliament-doores for poore widowes of ſouldiers? they cryed there till their throats were almoſt rent in ſunder, but nothing could be gotten but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civill language and harſh ſpeeches. And the poore Criple which hath loſt his Legs and Armes, ſome ten greats or a Noble to carry him where he was borne; We obſerve how Carts are loaded with them in the High-wayes, in which they lie miſerably diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in every reſpect; and when he comes to the place of his birth, or whether he is ſent, we beleeve he finds but courſe entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there, unleſſe it be curſes and imprecations upon his ſoule and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165117:6"/>body, for the good ſervice he has done his worthy Maſters, and the money he had will ſcarcely buy him a paire of crutches; Are not theſe brave rewards from our Grandees to us, their Creators, makers, and preſervers, as we have hitherto been? and by theſe meanes the poore ſouldier is ever hereafter utterly unable to help himſelfe, and the poore widdowes and hepleſſe children left comfortleſſe and deſtitute of any livelihood for want of their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands travell &amp; labour, but muſt neceſſarily turn beggar, and ſo muſt the poore criple Souldier. Have we not yet ſet forth (to you) rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſufficient, whoſe power is in your own hands by your unvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed ſwords, to unthrall your ſelves and make theſe your cruell Maſters to fall downe at your feet, and compell them to pay you your due rights, and wages, out of the mony and treaſure they have abundantly accumulated and hoorded up, by their keeping from us our juſt and merited wages, and by their robbing of the Country? Are our wages ſo great, that the Army-Taxes could not diſcharge them? but 'tis thought that they would doe more then pay us; and we know that all theſe Taxes through the whole Kingdome have been fully paid, and yet we unpaid. But ſuppoſe we had been paid, and exactly too, what a poore thing is it for ſo much a day to kill men, yea men of our owne Countrey (and we know not for what neither, except it be to ſatisfie the bloudy and aſpiring ſpirits of our Superiours) our owne kindred, our owne brothers, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure our owne fathers, our owne friends? Could you but imagine how we are excruciated in our tender conſciences for this floud of Crimſon bloud, that our hands are ſo deeply ſtained with, and the cruell and hard uſage whereby we have ſo oppreſſed our deare friends both in Countrey and City, you would preſently relent with us, and lay downe your ſwords, and mourne in duſt and aſhes all the dayes of your lives, and cry to God, and your oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed brethren, to pardon and forgive you; and if any of you have withall, you would moſt willingly make reſtitution to thoſe you have any wayes wronged, if your conſciences were any wayes touched as ours are. It may be God may be ſo mercifull to you as to touch your conſciences, and open your underſtandings, that you may before you depart this life ſee your bloudy ſinnes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent you of them, and not ſuffer you to goe out of this world
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165117:6"/>unrepented of them. We hope the Lord will in his good time doe theſe by you, and not let you end your dayes as Reprobates and Atheiſts. Thus we daily pray for you.</p>
            <p>But we cannot leave theſe <hi>Canniball</hi> monſters, but we muſt needs preſent to your further view the ſhort Epitomie of them. They are falſe Hypocrites to their God, meere Atheiſts, without naturall affection, Murtherers of their King (God forgive us this great ſinne, we cannot abſolutely cleare our ſelves of his Royall bloud,) very bloud-ſuckers; for they care not how many they kill, ſo they may be ſecured in their villany: Let the whole world be ruined, ſo that they may but enjoy their malitious ends, and evill gotten goods by betraying of their owne native Countrey; Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Tyrants (in reſpect they take and make themſelves abſolute Governours of the Commonwealth, contrary to the will and good liking of their Fellow-ſubjects and People) moſt extreme cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, for they have wracked the Common-wealth of all her trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and aſſumed it into their owne avaritious poſſeſſion; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-breakers, firſt with their God, with their Soveraigne, and the Parliament; Self-lovers, proud, and great boaſters of their own valour; but by our ſwords (ingratefull wretches to us their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments) by whoſe, only fortitude they are riſen (from the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill) to this greatneſſe; Keepers back of the hirelings wages, a ſinne crying in the eares of heaven againſt them; very impoſters, and the very ſcumme of all villany upon the earth, and ſo let them paſſe for very rogues and vagadonds. Now if any men that are not as they are can have any joy to ſerve ſuch Maſters, we wiſh that ſhame, miſery, infamy from the divine hand of Juſtice, at one time or other may certainly fall upon them, and they be partakers of their Maſters wretchedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Well then, are not we their ſtrength and power, that have made them thus imperious? Are not we thoſe that have made them thus dreadfull to the whole Kingdome of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> Why ſhould we then be ſuch ſots, that we ſhould be like unto the meere brutes, that have ſtrength and know it not? Let us but leave them, how contemptible would they be? How would they be jeared of all men? How ſoone would they be rooted and ſpued off from the face and ſurface of the earth? Would not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165117:7"/>
               <hi>England</hi> rejoyce to ſee her ſelfe rid of theſe devouring Locuſts, (they are ſo generally hated of God and all good people.) Oh! what a bleſſing would deſcend from heaven upon the earth, if God would be pleaſed to put this noble and gallant ſpirit in you all (our Fellow-ſouldiers) to vindicate our miſerable Nation from theſe devouring vermine? Doe you not obſerve how they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to deſtroy you? Are they not preparing for new Warres, to ſet you more by the eares than ever before, till yee have devoured one another? Doe they not lay heavier Taxes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you more than formerly? Doe they not eat up your Corne on which you and yours ſhould feed, and be nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with their Horſes and Souldiers? Doe they not devoure every manner of wayes? How ſoone would this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth be ſetled in peace, by Gods bleſſing, upon our deſerting of them? What bloudſhed would you keep off? What cruell op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion? How would good men and women bleſſe you, and children even yet unborne? How would all future Ages write and ſpeake of your worthineſſe? If you would free your Countrey, your Parents, your wives and children from theſe their enemies, who only ſeeke yours and their deſtruction? Would we be free our ſelves from their kicking, baſtonadoing, horſing, whipping hanging, ſhooting, and what not? Would you free your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Covntrey from forraigne Invaſion, cruell ſlaughter of innocent and harmleſſe people, from intolerable oppreſſion, and perpetuall ſlavery?</p>
            <p>Then let us boldly like good Chriſtians, loving Countrey-men, and Fellow-ſouldiers, unite our ſelves into one ſoule, and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to free our ſelves and our Countrey from the miſeries above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, leſt we be worſe than the very Turkiſh Janizaries; for they will be more excuſable than we, for they fighting againſt their own Countrey, naturall Parents, and their true Religion they were born under, is, becauſe they were taken away, and pulled from their Mothers breaſts in their Infancy, when they could not rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh their right hand from their left; but we in our Majority, and come to our diſcretion, and educated and brought up to ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Age, in the Chriſtian Religion; And for us (though we have been deceived by their faire pretences) yet now God hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165117:7"/>been pleaſed to diſcover unto us their hypocriſie, diſſembling and falſeneſſe; for us to be longer ſeduced by their diſſimulation, and ſo ſinne againſt our owne knowledge, in joyning with them in their falſities, and wickedneſſe, What a horrid ſhame will it be, not only to our owne perſons, but to the whole Nation, that ſuch Vipers ſhould be foſtered and nouriſhed in her!</p>
            <p>Let us boldly therfore demand of our Generall, and all his ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Officers, our full wages and hire that is due to us; Let us not be daunted to require our juſt and honeſt recompence for our hire and ſervice, we have ſerved for, even to a mite; and if they refuſe to pay it us, let us require it by the perill of their bloud; for we have ſpent our bloud, yea many have loſt their lives and limbes to bring them to this greatneſſe they are come to. They will ſay they have not to ſatisfie, that is all one, let us doe by them, as they have forced us (for want of our pay) to make the Countrey and City to pay their Taxes and Exciſe: we muſt have it, and will have it of them, neither will we be ſo put off by them: For they, their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers (take the Parliament Sitters, or ſetters amongſt them) have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient amongſt them to pay us to our deſires. We are well aſſured of what we ſpeake; The Taxes, Excize, Church-Land, Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, Compoſition, Cuſtoms, Forreſt-Lands, the waſte of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that they have waſted and throwne dawne in this Kingdome (to their perpetuall ſhame for ſuffering of it) Iriſh-Taxes, Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money, Pole-money, Propoſition-money, Theeviſh Plunder, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery; If all theſe vaſt ſummes could be Audited and preſented to the view of the eye, it would be a wonder to know the infinite treaſure they have grapled into their fingers and poſſeſsion, and notwithſtanding all theſe, that the hired common Souldier ſhould be in Arreares in ſo great ſummes for our wages, and for want of it to put the poore Countrey and City to ſuch vaſt expences by our quartering upon them. Theſe things rightly conſidered, it will make all honeſt men to ſtand amazed at their knavery, and unhoneſty for to cozen the common Souldier, and oppreſſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. And nevertheleſſe, that they have ingroſſed theſe vaſt ſummes, and the Common-wealth thus racked and impoveriſhed by them, yet the Souldiers Arreares of his juſt pay ſhould riſe and amount to divers 100000 pounds. Now doth it not appeare to you our Fellowſouldiers, what notable cheating has been amongſt the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165117:8"/>Parliaments, their Officers, and the Commanders of the Army? And what has made them thus falſe and impudent, but their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of our fortitude and ſtrength, as if we were the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for them to build all their villany, couſenage and oppreſſion upon? Its no marvell that we have loſt the love of our Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (as we have worthily deſerved) and only by reaſon of our unhoneſt Commanders, who unhoneſtly keep our money from us, and turne us to feed upon the barren Commons of <hi>England.</hi> We hope your eyes and underſtandings will be opened, and take theſe our writings into your conſideration, by whom all this while we have been thus wrong'd, miſled, and our juſt Rights kept from us, and how long we have lived, and ſtill are likely ſo to doe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we preſently take-ſome ſpeedy courſe to relieve our ſelves, out of the monies and meanes, and treaſure, our wiſe Maſters have grapled up to themſelves, or elſe we muſt be forced to oppreſſe the Countrey ſtill for food, or by ſtealing and theevery to get us raiment to cloath our nakedneſſe: but if you will be but men of courage, and cement our ſelves ſoundly together, doe not feare or doubt, but we will have our dues out of them with a murrain, and make the Cormorants diſgorge their ſtomacks of all their rich treaſure they have ſwallowed; We will make them glad to lay it at our feet, and pray us to accept of it. And by this courſe we ſhall pay our ſelves; for if this courſe be not taken by us, we ſhall vever be paid, nor the Country eaſed of future Taxes and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering: For they care not how immenſe the Arreares of the Army grows; for thereby they purpoſe hereafter to raiſe infinite ſummes of money upon the People, and put it into their pockets too; but we ſhall be never the better for it neither, but ſtill be fed on with a bit and a knock, as they do a ſetting-dog; and to take of them, what they ſhall think fit to give us.</p>
            <p>And we pray you all to obſerve their cunning fetch they have plotted to ſend us into <hi>Ireland,</hi> only to find themſelves matter for to ſet us a worke, and keep us from idleneſſe, leſt we ſhould pry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their deſignes. Firſt, what have we to doe with <hi>Ireland,</hi> to fight, and murther a People and Nation (for indeed they are ſet upon cruelty, and murthering poore people, which is all they glory in) which have done us no harme, only deeper to put our hands in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with their owne? we have waded too farre in that crimſon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165117:8"/>ſtreame (already) of innocent and Chriſtian bloud. Secondly, are they not afraid of us leſt we ſhould grow too unweldy, and too great for them to governe, and unhappily (againſt their deſire) we ſhould come to know their policy and knavery in managing their devilliſh and murtherous plots? And if they could but get us once over into <hi>Ireland</hi> (they thinke) they have us ſure enough: either we ſhall have our throats cut, or be famiſhed, for they are ſure we cannot get backe againe over the great Pond. We that have been old Souldiers, and have taſted longeſt of their barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe, its we they would be ſooneſt rid of; for the new No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, they ſuppoſe they may a while lead them by the noſes, as they have done us, by ſuffering of them like idle rogues to ride a horſeback up and downe the Countrey, and pill and powle the poore people, which may very well pleaſe them for a time; but alas they will find little benefit that way, becauſe we gave skim'd it ſo cleane over and over, that peradventure if the people ſhould be exaſperated againſt them, as who can tell what neceſſity and want at laſt may drive them to, perchance they may get that they unexpected: But it is us they feare; for if we periſh, then they think they are cock-ſure, beſides all our Arreares (which they never meane to pay us) will fall into their owne clutches. If they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from us our moneyes here in <hi>England,</hi> what will they doe in <hi>Ireland?</hi> when we cannot come to their faces to demand it, what hope is there that we ſhall ever have it? And if we have no pay but what they thinke fit, how ſhall we live? But in caſe we have money, what ſhall we doe with money? we cannot eat it (perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture they hope to tempt us with a little ready money in our hands) for victuals and clothing will be ſo difficult to be had there, that (notwithſtanding our money) we may be all ſtarved; but they will make you beleeve, that victuals and all other proviſion and neceſſaries, ſhall be convayed out of <hi>England;</hi> let us be no longer gull'd with that fopperie, for we too too well know the ſcarcitie of all things in <hi>England,</hi> that nothing can be affoorded out of it; and if here it be not to be had, how is it poſſible to be brought from hence thither? And have we not very well obſerved, how often this poore State has been cheated with ſending reliefe into <hi>Ireland,</hi> which never went, but all converted into their graſping
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165117:9"/>clawes, and poore <hi>Ireland</hi> loſt for want of it, and now (at their pleaſure) we muſt be ſent to recover it? Beſides, are we not ey-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes how many poore Souldiers and other People come daily from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and cry out they are ſtarved, and want their pay worſe than we doe? neither if we want our pay, can we find the free quarter we have here. So in concluſion, we are like neither to get neceſſaries or money there; a faire encouragement to make us goe. But I hope by what is here ſet downe, our Brother-ſouldier will well conſider before he goes, and firſt get in their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that is already due, and then we will talke further upon this undertaking-voyage. Neither will they find it ſo eaſie a matter to be ſo rid of us, as they ſuppoſe to doe by all their cunning and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy. But one more caſe will we put you: ſuppoſe we had money to our deſires, proviſion ſufficient in <hi>England</hi> to be ſent us, Yet what danger and hazard will there be to conveigh it over to us? for if it ſhould be ſurprized, or caſt away, or wind-bound, what ſhall become of us, are we not in a lamentable caſe? And why muſt we goe over thither under all theſe hazards and danger of our owne lives, only to kill the people there, that our Tyrannicall Maſters may the eaſier rule over a few, &amp; poor ſort of baſe people? and for this reaſon we muſt venture bodies, ſoules and lives, to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill their wils and pleaſures; ſurely we have great cauſe to doe it for them, they have been ſuch gracious Maſters to us. We hope theſe reaſons will make any ſenſible men adviſe with their pillow, before they will voluntarily and raſhly run themſelves upon this Rock, and let <hi>Ireland</hi> be quiet; except there may be better reaſons readred, than we underſtand yet.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
